hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today we will see about
at theate profile annotation very very
important right and you will find
certain new stuff in this that what is
profiling okay but before we start
profile in the previous topic I have
told you about adate conditional on
property annotation right so you already
know that what's conditional on property
if you haven't seen just check it out
because they are interconnected how I
will tell you so in just one quick recap
at the rate conditional on property what
does it says that bean is created
conditionally means a bean can be
created or not okay so how we can
control whether a bean is uh required or
not so through this annotation here we
in the application. properties we
provide this configuration SQL
connection.
enabled and this value get match up if
it is equal then only Bean will get
created otherwise Bean will not get
created okay and I have asked this
question okay if you have two
application if you have two application
and one common code
base how you will make sure that bean is
only created for for one application not
for other okay so most of the answers
were at theate conditional on property
which is expected one and also many
Engineers also said that we can also
achieve through at theate profile
annotation and we will use at theate
profile annotation okay so today I will
touch up this point because this is very
important to understand the proper use
of profile so yes you can achieve the
same functionality through at theate
profile
annotation but technically at theate
profile is intended for environment
separation rather than application is
specific Bean creation what does it mean
Shan like don't
worry I will get in depth of this right
so we will understand the profile better
but for now you need to see that yes
with profile also this is possible to do
a bean can be created only for one
application and for other this Bean will
not be created
itself but this is not the you can say
that technically it's not correct but it
can be done and we will come to this
question again at last once we
understand the atate profile
annotation okay let's Deep dive into at
theate profile annotation to understand
it better consider this scenario
that you have a DB and you are running
certain code in your local machine so
some some says local machine some says
de development okay so username and
password which you are using to connect
to a database might be certain different
so it's like Dave username Dave
password but if the same code you are
running on a stage machine or in a QA
environment
right so maybe the username and the
password might be different to connect
to a
database okay and
similarly the same code if you are
running in live of production the
username and
password might be different than your
local machine and then State machine
right so username and password might be
different to connect to a
database so
we have different type of environments
when we work the same
code okay when it refers to a particular
configuration so here the configuration
is username and password so when I'm
running into my local system I might I
might don't have to give anything I have
configured like username and password
should be empty in QA it should be like
some certain dummy username password
password we can put same username same
password but in stage or in production
it should be a valid username valid
password okay so the same code but the
configuration is different based upon
the environment which you are
working how you will and generally one
more thing this username and password is
just one
example there are so many other
configurations which are different for
different
environments okay so Dave QA and live
production so there are so many things
like URL and port number so maybe when
you're connecting to certain you this is
your app you are connecting to some
other
application some other application
dependent application so maybe the URL
you are connecting and the port number
you are connecting might be different so
port number here is
45613 in QA it might be same 45613 but
in live it is different
65121 what I'm trying to say is that the
URL and port number can be another
configuration which can be different
based on the environment so there are
other parameters like connection timeout
request timeout values these also
differs based upon different environment
okay so your live resources your live
machine has too much resource your
development machine your local machine
is not that capable compared to the live
machines similarly QA machines might be
better than Dave but not better than the
production so the connection timeout
value might be you you might uh you
might need connection uh time in
millisecond might be here you want th000
milliseconds for Connection in QA you
might need 500 but in live you require
only let's say 50 milliseconds so these
value also differs based upon
environment similarly throttle value
retry values you might want more retries
in Dave than in QA than in live okay so
username and password is just one
example what I want to say in short
there are so many different parameters
different configuration which you need
different for
different
environments so how you will achieve it
how you will do
it because we put the configurations in
application. properties
file but how to handle different
environment configuration so these are
the configuration but it's different for
Dave these are the configuration
different for QA similarly for live
different
configurations but till now we have seen
only okay there is only one file
application. properties how in this
single file we will put all three
different
configuration okay that's where the
profiling comes into the picture okay
I'm not telling you about at theate
profile annotation now first you need to
understand profiling to understand the
add theate profile annotation okay so at
theate uh the profiling comes into the
picture at this point of the time so
what does profiling means in a spring
boot so we have a file called
application. properties okay so we can I
told you that we can have different
environments in a springboard you can
say that we can have different
profiles okay like and you can have
multiple application. properties like
this application hyphen your profile
one.
properties application hyphen profile 2
do properties similarly like different
environments you have different profiles
you have so what I told you that the
profile in a spring boot is nothing but
equivalent to your environment
so if you have application hyph Dave do
properties so this property will contain
all the configuration which you required
only for
Dave so you have another for QA right
for stage testing so application hyphen
qa. properties this will all the
configuration which you required for
your
QA similarly for your let's say hyphen
live. properties application hyphen
live.
properties okay so we can have multiple
applications profiles based upon the
environments you
have okay so see this
part see this example so I have
application. properties in that I have
provided a username and password and
certain default
values and I have created
multiple
profiles right and you know when I said
profiles means multiple environment
specific application. properties so
application hyund dave. properties so
this is my profile one so there if you
say username and password is Dave
username Dave
password similarly I created second
profile application hyphen qa.
properties and its username password is
different QA username QA
password similarly for live I have a
configuration inside application hyphen
prod. properties and username password
is prod usern Name Pro
password okay so now this under uh
consider this code very very simple code
a simple class with atate component
annotation means it is getting managed
by Spring
boot I have two
parameters which are annotated with
atate value means this this value is
getting filled up from this
configuration application. properties
configuration okay so this field is
getting filled from username spring boot
will search this name into a
application. properties
file similarly the password is getting
filled from same at theate value means
application. properties
file and after the post construct means
when the bean is constructed I am just
printing this value what is the username
what is the password very very simple
you already know it because we have
already seen this
examples now when I run the application
what would happen when you run the
application spring boot will find this
at theate component and since it is
single ter means it is eligible for
eager
initialization so spring boot will
create a bean out of it and will try to
then once Bean is created it will try to
resolve this dependencies so it will try
to fill up this username and password so
it will look application do properties
now there are multiple application do
properties present which one to pick it
will see that hey any profile is
set do have we set any profiles still
yet nothing we just have created
multiple properties
files but we haven't set currently we
are working on which profile so which
one it will pick this default default
one so application do properties
considered is as your
default if you haven't set any profile
that hey I working on this Dave I'm
working on this QA or I'm working on
this prod
production then springboard will pick
this
default okay and it will try to see that
hey username is present here yes so it
will fill this default username in this
similarly password it will fill default
password Here and it will proceed
further so now here if you
see when the starting the application
what is the username it got printed
default username default
password okay so because till now we
haven't set the
profile okay so now we have seen this
now you can ask me hey how to set the
profile then if I want to pick let's say
I am working in QA I want to set this
profile or and I wanted this
configuration to pick up actually to
connect to my database how to do
that so what we have to do is we have to
use this configuration spring. profiles.
active we have to set this
configuration so how generally we do
this in application.
properties right which is generally you
can say the default one you can put
this configuration spring. profiles.
active and whatever the profile which
you wanted so this is the profiles right
either Dave whatever you can give any
name
development local anything but the same
name you have to provide here so
Dave QA or prod so these are the profile
so whichever profile you wanted a spring
boot to pick you can provide in this
configuration
so here now what I have given is in this
application.
properties this profile I have set to
QA okay and the same example nothing
change in this class nothing change in
this all three now when I started the
application you will see that spring
boot has set the profile what the
profile is set to QA okay so when you
start an spring boot application what
happen is the spring boot app look for
this configuration and see that hey any
specific profile I need to set if
yes if if it find this then what it will
do is you will see this message that
this is the profile is got
set so QA so now springbot internally
will look for application hyph qa.
properties so it found this so now it
will use this okay so now consider this
as a parent child so so if username is
present here username is present here
this will get now
prioritized okay if let's say some some
configuration XY
Z is present here but it is not present
here right and your code is referring to
that hey look for XY Z and even though
we have set the profile to QA the XY Z
is not here so but it's there in the
parent it will use this so you got it
what I'm trying to say that consider
this as a parent configuration this is
as a child configuration if value is
present in both the child one will get
priority otherwise if value is not
presented to child but presented to the
parent the parent one will be used okay
and if it is not there in the parent and
if it is there in the child child one
will be used and if it is present in
both the child one will get
priority okay so now here when I run the
app apption you will see that yeah
spring boot had set the profile QA
because of
this and while getting when uh spring
boot encounter this class with the adate
component it will try to fill up this
value now it will see that okay username
and password is present into
application. properties and also its
profile QA application doore qa.
properties so it will give priority to
this one so QA username and QA password
will get fill up
here got it so spring. profiles. active
is the one which tells spring boot that
which specific profile you are working
at all right so which configuration you
have to pick either this either this or
either
this now you can ask one question that
hey sh okay it's good that in
application. properties we can provide
like we can give by default that hey by
default every every time da only but
dynamically I want to change let's say
my I'm going to start my application in
live I don't want to change it to here
like uh production every time and all
right so by default I given that it
should be working as a Dave but how to
set this
dynamically so this is how generally
done so there are two ways I will tell
you two ways how it's done currently in
live
applications so ultimately what we have
to do is during application startup we
have to tell spring Boot and set this
configuration hey Spring boot uh this is
the
configuration we have set use that
specific environment how to tell that so
currently when you when this is started
this is started through intellig in
intellig you get run option right right
so intellig when you just click on
button run right ultimately internally
it's running the command only so this is
the actual command to run the spring
boot so Mayan spring boot colon run so
this actually starts the spring boot
application okay like similarly how it
is starting the similar way if you run
this this much may one spring hyphen
boot colon run so this will start your
spring boot
application now we want to give in a
runtime dynamically that which
environment you are currently working at
so we can give like
this so hyund d means you are setting
and during you are setting some
environment variable right you're
setting some property so hyphen D now
spring hyph boot do run do profiles so
means during run application startup
Spring boot. Run so this is you are
running a spring boot right so spring
boot. run. profiles you set to
prod okay so what it internally it will
do is it will set this the spring.
profiles. active to
prod even though you have application do
properties you have given Dave but if
you are setting it dynamically in the
environment this will get more
priority okay if you don't don't give it
then it will use the default one which
you have given in the application.
properties if you provided this one then
this will your ultimate priority this
will be given the first
priority okay so whenever you are
running an application in Live or QA
right so you can run using this and
provide whether which environment you
are working whether in QA prod Dave
whatever
okay there is another way
that in in if you're working you might
check your company's pom.xml file you
will see something called
profiles the same thing which we are
setting right this spring hyph boot.
run.
profile the same thing we can set
through we can uh add this configuration
into Mayan so these are the different
profiles I have added into p. XML so
first profile is I have given name local
this ID is unique so you can give
anything so I have given local and the
property in this one is springy boot.
run. profiles the same thing this
one so Dave I want to set into this when
this is
chosen so this is the second profile
which I have given a name
production so whenever this ID is chosen
what is the profile I want to set
prod and the third profile I have set is
that which I have given a name stage
when this ID is chosen what is the
profile I want to set
QA okay now during Mayan spring boot
application command Mayan spring boot
run all we have to tell that which
configuration to pick I have just tell
hyphen P hyphen p means you have to pick
a particular profile from
a Mayan pom.xml which one production one
so production one this ID so what it
will do is it will set this property H
spring boot. run. profile prod this is
just different way of doing what we are
doing
here so here we have done the same thing
but
without pom.xml so that's why we have to
to set the
complete configuration
here otherwise in the pom.xml you can
set this values only during application
startup you can tell that okay which one
to pick either this either this or this
and the same thing the same
configuration will get set with this
value so both are doing the same thing
but one through pom.xml and another is
without pom.xml whichever you
like generally this uh in the
applications live application this is
mostly preferred like it's clear right
the command is generally clear that you
want to run it like for a production for
stage for local because you give proper
naming
okay so here if you see that when I run
this
command may1 spring boot run hyph D
spring boot run profiles
praud even though it's whatever it is
present here what happen is a spring.
profile is set to prod and when you run
it you will see prod username prod
password okay profile is set to
prod so do you understand now what
profiling is
right you understand now profiling is
right what profiling is we have
different environments and for different
environments we have different
configurations those are environments in
spring board generally known as
profiles so we have to choose a
particular profile when running the
application if you don't choose default
one will be choosen if you have to
choose specifically you have to set the
spring. profiles. active
configuration okay now with that being
said now let's see what is atate profile
annotation then I understand the
profiling but what is atate profile
annotation so using atate profile
annotation we can tell spring boot to
create a bean only when particular
profile is
set now here in this just see an example
I'll tell you with this example again in
the application. properties username
password what is the profile I set
QA similarly Dave QA prod is files are
present but profile is set to this
now here if you see that I have created
two classes one is my SQL connection
this is a add component managed by
Spring Boot and I have put the profile
is atate profile annotation
prod similarly there is another class
called No SQL atate component and what
is the profile I have said
Dave now as per the definition what it
says that it tells spring boot to create
Bean only when a particular profile is
set so now when you started an
application May one spring boot run
either through intellig or you run this
command both are the same thing what it
what it will happen so first during
application startup it will set its
profile to
QA okay it will set its profile to QA
because spring. profiles. activ set to
QA now it will find this
class with adate component and since it
is single turn can be eagly initialized
so it will springboard will try to
create its beam but then it identify at
theate profile annotation and it say
that
hey I have to create only its Bean when
this profile is set prud but currently
what is the profile is set QA so you can
say that it's a string matching so is
prod equals to equals to QA like strings
do equals like something you can do
right so is it matching prod and QA
matching no so this profile will uh this
Bean will not be
created then springboard will find no
SQL connection class and it see that hey
can I create a bean of this okay I have
to create it Bean only when Dave profile
is set so what is the profile is set
currently QA they are not matching so
this Bean will also not get created so
here if you see when I started the
application this two are not getting
printed so these are not created B is
not
created now I am just uh with the same
example right even though in the
application. properties QA is present
but while running the
application I am dynamically setting
that he set the profile to
prod and when I run the application here
here if you see what profile is set prod
now during uh Bean initialization it
will find this MySQL connection it will
find the profile hey okay I have to
create the bean only when prod this
profile is set so p o it's going to
match with this V it's match right so
here if you see my SQL prod username
prod password is
set okay because of this
configuration prod configuration
spring boot will try to pick the name
which you have given right PR so
application hyph pr. properties so it
found found this also so username
password is set this and also because of
this ad theate profile it matches that
this is matching with the
profile or not if it match then only
Bean will get created no SQL here if you
see that it's set to Dave but our
profile is pro so it don't match so my
uh no SQL is bean is not even
created okay so you got it that add
theate profile annotation what it does
it it tells spring boot to create a bean
only when a
specific a
specific profile is
set okay so there is one more thing I
want to tell that don't get confused
with this that we can also set multiple
profiles at a
time so here if you see that spring.
profiles. active prore QA see this is
doesn't make sense you can't work in two
environment at the same time you can't
work in prod and QA at the same time
okay but you can provide comma separated
prore Q so what would happen is whatever
the last you have that would be picked
actually okay so spring profiles. active
so which which application properties
would be used qa1 the last
one but this comma separated is mostly
helpful in at theate profile because
multiple profiles are set so here if you
see I have given prore QA so this class
when the spring will try to create a
bean it will set that hey profile prod
yes it is
set for this class no SQL connection
what is the profile QA yes this is also
Al set so both will get created so here
if you see both will get
created because both profiles are set
but which application do properties it
will pick the last one QA so it will
pick QA QA username QA password for
both QA username for my SQL QA username
for no SQL also
okay so you can give comma separated so
only one application do properties would
be pick only the last one but the since
but the profiles will set to all uh all
these profiles will get set which might
help in this
annotation
okay so now let's come back to the
previous question which I asked starting
you have two application you have two
application and one common code base how
you will make sure that bean is only
created for one application not for
another so the is like this is a common
code base
okay in this one I have given a profile
F1 okay now this is application one in
application One application. Properties
I have set spring. profiles. active
app1 and in application two I have set
spring. profiles. active app 2 so during
this application startup what is the
profile will set app one and for this
one during application startup profiles
got set to app two now during when
spring uh find this and it tried to
create a bean it will say that hey if
this profile is set have fun so only for
this Bean would get created here app to
doesn't so Bean will not get created for
this so yes we can achieve it but see
again this is not enironment your F1 is
not
enironment okay your app2 is not
envirment envirment is like development
environment St stage environment live
production
environment even though we are able to
achieve the this
part right conditionally creation of
being but making use of profile to
achieve this is
something if I am the pr reviewer I will
not accept it because the purpose of
profiling is
different you might understand that I
because I have told you what is
profiling before even tell you at the
profile annotation what's the actual
purpose of this profiling different
environments so when you're setting this
F1 so I am uh specifically that you have
like application hyph F1 do properties
that doesn't make sense because in every
application you can either have
application. properties and different
environment like Dave QA
production so this doesn't make sense to
have this so This create confusion hey
what is this is this like profile is
generally everybody understand as an
envirment right so use at theate
conditional on property rather than
using
profile
for conditionally creation of be okay so
while telling you at theate profile
annotation I have told you that why this
is the correct answer why this is not
even though we can achieve the same but
still I want to hear you on the comment
section what do you think and if there
is anything we can discuss more thank
you guys bye